The Life Of Muhammad ﷺ, The Makkan Period,
By Imam Anwar Al-Awlaki,
اَعُوْذُ بِاللهِ مِنَّ الشِّيْطَانِ الرَّجِيْمِ۝بِسْمِ اللهِ الرَّحْمَانِ الرَّحِيْمَ۝
اَلْحَمْدُ لله وَالصَّلَاةُ وَالسَّلَامُ عَلى سَيِّدِنَا محمد وَعَلَى اَلِهِ وَصَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ تَسْلِيْمًا كَثِيْرا
Lessons from the journey of Rasool Allah ﷺ to At-Taef(ألطائف).
Zaid Bin Harissa(زيد بن حارثه) was the one protecting Rasool Allah ﷺ from the rocks,
that were being thrown at Muhammad صلوات الله وسلام عليه.
So, Zaid Bin Harissa(زيد بن حارثه) was protecting Rasool Allah ﷺ shielding him with his own body.
In the Battle of Uhud(احد), we have similar stories of Sahabah(صحابہ) using their backs
not just to protect Rasool Allah ﷺ from rocks like in this incident,
but to protect him from arrows.
This was the level of sacrifice that the Sahabahرضي الله عنهم had.
Now we might not have a chance to protect Rasool Allah ﷺ with our physical bodies.
So, if we missed that chance, let's make it up, by protecting Rasool Allah ﷺ through defending his message,
through protecting his honor,
through teaching others about his life, Muslims and non Muslims, let's do our part.
Abu Muslim Al-Khaulaani(ابو مسلم الخولاني) one of the greatest of At-Tabaeen(التابعين), he said;
Do the companions of Rasool Allah ﷺ think that
we will let them, have Rasool Allah ﷺ for themselves?
No, we're going to compete with them.
We want to get our share of the Messenger of Allah.
So, even though we're living centuries past the time of Muhammadﷺ
so we cannot participate physically, in helping him, in his mission
but it's not too late.
There's a lot that we could do.
That would resemble what Zaid Bin Harissa(زيد بن حارثه) did on that day.
It might not ever be as great as what Zaid Bin Harissa(زيد بن حارثه) did or what Talha(طلحه) did on the day of Uhud(احد)
but at least we can try and do something.
And when we study the Seerah(سيرة) of Rasool Allah ﷺ, and when we developed love for him
it needs to encourage us to go through the same footsteps that the students of Rasool Allah ﷺ went through.
The second lesson, when Rasool Allah ﷺ was speaking to the people of At-Taef(ألطائف).
No one responded to him, they all rejected him.
But remember what we said, Do good because you never know what the outcome will be.
Rasool Allah ﷺ was chased out of At-Taef(ألطائف).
So, he might have thought that his words did not really leave an effect on them.
But among the crowds Rasool Allah ﷺ was speaking to, was a child.
His name is Khalid Al-Udwaan(خالدالعدواني),
he's a member of the tribe of Thaqeef(ثقيف).
He said: I was standing there listening to the speech of Rasool Allah ﷺ in the fair grounds of At-Taef(ألطائف)
and I heard the messenger of Allah recites Surah-At-Tariq(سورة الطارق).
And I remembered it then, when I was still an non believer.
And when I became Muslim, I already knew that Surah(سورة).
So, here we have Rasool Allah ﷺ giving a speech to adults, nobody cared about what Rasool Allah ﷺ said,
but there was a child in there who remembered and memorized Surah-At-Tariq(سورة الطارق)
by listening to it, from the mouth of Rasool Allah ﷺ in At-Taef(ألطائف),
and years later, Rasool Allah ﷺ is seeing the harvest of the seed that he planted in At-Taef(ألطائف).
So, do good, because you never know what the outcome will be.
Number three,
we talked about what happened between Rasool Allah ﷺ and Addaas(عداس),
didn't you remember Addaas(عداس), the Christian.
Over here, you have an example of Da'wah(دعوة) through action.
Rasool Allah ﷺ started by saying Bismillah(بسم الله) an Islamic act.
This Islamic act even though it seems simple and small, was the cause of the Islam of Addaas(عداس).
Because Addaas(عداس) never heard this before, in this land of the Arabs.
They don't say Bismillah(بسم الله), they don't start in the name of Allah.
And that opened up a conversation between Rasool Allah ﷺ and Addaas(عداس)
that ended up with Addaas(عداس), admitting the Prophet hood of Muhammadﷺ and believing in him.
So, sometimes you might do something without paying attention,
but it's attracting the attention of others around you.
And that might open the door for them to have some curiosity,
and that will be the beginning of their studying of Islam,
which might end with them accepting the religion of Allah.
So, sometimes our Da'wah(دعوة) could be indirectly through our action.
And the reputation of the Sahabahرضي الله عنهم that they developed after Islam
had a major role in attracting many of the other Arabs to Islam.
So, it wasn't necessarily their words, but it was their behavior, their character, the way they changed in Islam.
Now Rasool Allah ﷺ had to leave At-Taef(ألطائف), he was rejected by the people in At-Taef(ألطائف)
and we said earlier that with difficulty comes ease.
إِنَّ مَعَ الْعُسْرِ يُسْرًا
Rasool Allah ﷺ went through a difficult time, hardship in At-Taef(ألطائف).
Allahسبحانه وتعالى followed it with a blessing.
Rasool Allah ﷺ was reciting Qur'an in the desert and some Jinn(جن) happened to be in the area.
And the words of Qur'an attracted them.
And they came to Rasool Allah ﷺ and learned from him, verses of Qur'an and ended up becoming Muslim.
What are Jinn(جن)?
Jinn(جن) is a world of creatures that has intelligence, lives with us on earth
have quite a similar structure, life structure like we do,
they have clans, families, tribes, nations, they speak different dialects, languages follow different religions.
So, they are pretty similar to human beings.
The difference is that they were created from fire, we were created from clay,
they see us and we don't see them.
But there are Jinn(جن) who are Christian, there are Muslim Jinn(جن), there are Jewish Jinn(جن)
There are Jinn who speak Arabic, Jinn(جن) who speak English, Jinn(جن) who speak Russian.
And they might even follow the customs of the land that they live in.
And many of these supernatural or strange events that people talk about and you see on the front pages of tabloids
a sighting of a UFO and all of those interesting things, might easily be explained as Jinn(جن).
There is an intelligent world is living with us on earth.
And these haunted places and all of this can be explained easily by Muslims, it's not a big deal for us.
Ya'ani(يعني) we have all of this mythology that is surrounding, this supernatural events
and you have a whole entertainment industry that is based on it and movies and stories and Halloween and all that stuff,
when there's simple thing behind it and that is that there is a world of creatures living with us that we cannot see.
Sometimes we might have sightings of them but most of the time we don't.
While they have access to us and they can see us.
So, these Jinn(جن) came to Rasool Allah ﷺ and became Muslim.
Now there might have been more than one incident in which Jinn(جن) came to Rasool Allah ﷺ and became Muslim
because we have the story of Al-Jinn(جن) is mentioned twice in Qur'an
once in Surah Jinn(سورة الجن) and once in Surah Ah'qaaf(سورة الأحقاف)
the verses of Surah Ah'qaaf(سورة الأحقاف),
وَإِذْ صَرَفْنَا إِلَيْكَ نَفَرًا مِنَ الْجِنِّ يَسْتَمِعُونَ الْقُرْآنَ
فَلَمَّا حَضَرُوهُ قَالُوا أَنْصِتُوا ۖ
فَلَمَّا قُضِيَ وَلَّوْا إِلَىٰ قَوْمِهِمْ مُنْذِرِينَ۝
قَالُوا يَا قَوْمَنَا إِنَّا سَمِعْنَا كِتَابًا أُنْزِلَ مِنْ بَعْدِ مُوسَىٰ
كِتَابًا أُنْزِلَ مِنْ بَعْدِ مُوسَىٰ مُصَدِّقًا لِمَا بَيْنَ يَدَيْهِ
يَهْدِي إِلَى الْحَقِّ وَإِلَىٰ طَرِيقٍ مُسْتَقِيمٍ۝
And mention, O Muhammad(محمد) when we directed to you a few of the Jinn(جن) listening to the Qur'an.
And when they attended it, they said listen quietly.
And when it was concluded, they went back to their people as Warner's
They said: O our people indeed we have heard a recited book revealed after Moses
confirming what was before it, which guides to the truth and to a straight path.
One commentator of Qur'an, who gave Tafseer(تفسير), asks this following question.
He says, How come the Jinn(جن) said that we have heard something that was revealed after Musa(موسى),
and they didn't say after Eesa(عيسى),
how come the Jinn(جن) brought up the name of Moses and didn't bring up the name of Jesus.
And his explanation was that these Jinn(جن) were Jewish.
And they were following the message of Musa(موسى).
So, when they heard Qur'an.
They said: This is a revelation that is coming after the revelation that was given to Musa(موسى)
and this commentator says that these Jinn(جن) actually, were from Yemen, where there were some Jews.
That's one way to look at the verse, it's not necessarily the only view
but it's also an indication that the Jinn(جن) would follow the customs of the people in their area.
They said, O our people, indeed we have heard the recited book revealed after Musa(موسى)
confirming what was before it and guides to the truth and to a straight path.
يَا قَوْمَنَا أَجِيبُوا دَاعِيَ اللَّهِ وَآمِنُوا بِهِ
يَغْفِرْ لَكُمْ مِنْ ذُنُوبِكُمْ وَيُجِرْكُمْ مِنْ عَذَابٍ أَلِيمٍ۝
وَمَنْ لَا يُجِبْ دَاعِيَ اللَّهِ فَلَيْسَ بِمُعْجِزٍ فِي الْأَرْضِ وَلَيْسَ لَهُ مِنْ دُونِهِ أَوْلِيَاءُ ۚ
أُولَٰئِكَ فِي ضَلَالٍ مُبِينٍ۝
O our people respond to the caller of Allah and believe in Him,
He, Allah will forgive you, your sins and protect you from a painful punishment.
But he, who does not respond to the caller of Allah will not cause failure to Him upon earth
and he will not have besides him any protectors, those are in manifest errors.
So, this was an example of something good that happened to Rasool Allah ﷺ, after something that was difficult.
This is mentioned to happen after At-Taef(ألطائف).
Rasool Allah ﷺ now has to enter into Makkah again.
Now getting in, is not like leaving, you could leave easily, but it's not easy to get into Makkah again
especially after the news reached to Makkah,
that Rasool Allah ﷺ, has went to preach his message to the people of At-Taef(ألطائف).
So, now Rasool Allah ﷺ is not able to go into Makkah again.
He has to seek the protection of someone in order to enter into his own town.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ is now camping outside of Makkah,
trying to find somebody who would sponsor him and give him protection.
He sent a message with a man named Uraiqat(عريقت), to go to a Al-Akhnas Bin Shuraiq(ألأخنس بن شريق).
Now, Al-Akhnas Bin Shuraiq(ألأخنس بن شريق) was living in Makkah.
He was an ally of the people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ), even though he wasn't one of them.
So, when Al-Akhnas(ألأخنس) received the message from Muhammadﷺ, he said;
Since I'm an ally of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ), I cannot give protection to somebody, who's from Quraish(قُرَيْشْ).
I'm only an ally, I cannot go over my authority
and give protection to somebody who's from the tribe whom, I'm an ally of.
So, Al-Akhnas Bin Shuraiq(ألأخنس بن شريق) turned down the request.
Muhammadﷺ sent the same message again, to Sohail Bin Amr(سهيل ابن عمرو),
Sohail Bin Amr(سهيل ابن عمرو) said, I cannot give you protection
because the clan of Amr Bin Loae(عمرو بن لؤئي) cannot give protection to somebody who's from Ka'ab Bin Loae(كعب بن لؤئي).
Rasool Allah ﷺ tried the third time and he sent this time a message, a request to Mut'am Bin Udae(مطعم بن عدي).
Mut'am Bin Udae(مطعم بن عدي) did accept the request.
And Muhammadﷺ went and spent the night at his house early in the morning,
Al-Mut'am(المطعم) asked six or seven of his sons to carry their swords and to put on some special clothes
and to go out surrounding Muhammadﷺ and to escort him to Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه).
When they reached their they had a seat, over watching Muhammadﷺ, while he was making Tawaf(طواف).
So, Abu Sufiyan(ابوسفيان) came to Al-Mut'am(المطعم)
and told him: Are you giving him protection, or are you following him?
Al-Mut'am(المطعم) said: I'm only giving him protection.
Abu Sufiyan(ابوسفيان) said: If that's the case, we will accept your protection.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ now is giving Da'wah(دعوة) in Makkah under the protection of Al-Mut'am Bin Jubair(المطعم بن جبير).
Rasool Allah ﷺ after the passing away of Abu Talib(ابو طالب) and Khadijah(خديجه)
and seeing the stalemate that the mission reached in Makkah,
even though there was still some converts trickling in,
but overall it was reaching to a stagnating state, and many avenues were being blocked.
So, the Messenger of Allah felt the necessity of finding an alternative base
somewhere where he can have freedom to propagate the message.
And he was actively pursuing that goal by meeting with the Arab tribes,
Arab delegates, during the season of pilgrimage,
because that is a time when people come from all over Arabia to one location, Makkah.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ would devote the days of Hajj(حَجْ) to visiting the camps of the Arabs,
he would visit every tribe in their campground, and give them Da'wah(دعوة) and ask them for protection.
Az-Zuhri(ألزهري) states;
The Messenger of Allah would, for the period of those years present himself to the Arab tribes at each fair
speaking with each tribal leader, but asking them only for their protection and support.
He would say;
I don't wish to force any of you to do anything.
Any of you who agree to what I asked may do so.
But I would not compel anyone not so wishing.
All I want, is to guard myself against those, who want to kill me,
so that I may fulfill my Lord's mission
and carry out whatever decree He wishes regarding myself and those who support me.
And then, Az-Zuhri(ألزهري) says, but not one of them accepted him.
Every one of those tribes reached the following conclusion,
the man's own tribe knew him best,
how could we accept as suitable for us,
someone who has subverted his tribe, and whom they have expelled.
Since his tribe did not accept him, they know best, that was their conclusion.
By the way, Az-Zuhri(ألزهري) is one of the early Muslim scholars.
He was among the generation of At-Tabaeen(ألتابعين) or little later than that.
And he was the one, who was given the responsibility of compiling Hadith(حديث),
which happened during the time of Umar Bin Abdel Aziz(عمر بن عبدالعزيز).
This was the first official project to compile the Hadith(حديث) of Rasool Allah ﷺ,
and the one entrusted with this mission was Az-Zuhri(ألزهري)
and the one, who appointed him to that position was the Khalifah(خليفه) himself, Umar Bin Abdel Aziz(عمر بن عبدالعزيز).
So, again, these were the words of Az-Zuhri(الزهري).
Ibn Is'haqq(اِبْنِ اِسْحَاقْ) stated that Ibn Shahabah Az-Zohri(ابن شهاب الزهري), again is relating to him
that Muhammadﷺ visited some of the tribes and he narrates the story of visiting the tribe of Kinda(كنده).
Rasool Allah ﷺ went to them gave them Da'wah(دعوة).
They refused him.
Rasool Allah ﷺ next, went to a tribe or a clan called Bannu Abdillah(بنو عبدالله),
the sons of AbdAllah(عبدالله).
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ went to them explaining Islam and then he told them
and look at how Allah has chosen for you, a good name.
You are the sons of AbdAllah(عبدالله) but also they turned him down.
Next Rasool Allah ﷺ went to the tribe of Bannu Hanifah(بنو حنيفه).
And they treated Rasool Allah ﷺ so bad,
Az-Zuhri(ألزهري) says none of the Arabs gave him so rude a rejection as they did.
And Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله), these same people Bannu Hanifah(بنو حنيفه) are the ones, who years later
are going to lead the worst revolt ever against Muhammadﷺ,
which happened right before he died,
and was only ended in the time of Abu Bakr As-Siddiqueرضي الله عنه
and this revolt was led by Musailima Al Kazzab(مسيلمه الكذاب).
Musailima Al Kazzab(مسيلمه الكذاب) was from the tribe of Bannu Hanifah(بنوحنيفه).
Musailima Al Kazzab(مسيلمه الكذاب) is the man, who claimed Prophet hood.
And this was the greatest revolt
and one of the worst battles that occurred against the Muslim armies.
Next, Rasool Allah ﷺ went to the campgrounds of the tribe of Bannu Aamir Bin Sa'saa(بنوعامر بن صعصعة).
Bannu Aamir Bin Sa'saa(بنوعامر بن صعصعة), when their leader Bayhara Bin Faraas(بيحرة بن فراس) met Rasool Allah ﷺ,
and saw him and listen to his words.
He became so impressed by what he saw.
So, Bayhara(بيحرة) said;
I swear if I were to have this brave man of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ), I could eat up the Arabs with him.
Now, Bayhara(بيحرة) is thinking politics.
He wants to recruit Muhammadﷺ.
Why.?
To conquer the lands of the Arabs
because he saw that Muhammadﷺ possess qualities that were unique.
So, he told Muhammadﷺ;
If we were to follow your orders,
and then Allah gave you a victory against those opposing you,
would we have power after you were gone.
So, the response of Muhammadﷺ was that,
اَلْاَرْضُ لِله يُوْرِثُهَا مَنْ يَشَاءْ وَ الْعَاقِبَة لِلْمُتَّقِيْنْ
That the earth belongs to Allah, and He will give power, to whomever He wishes.
In other words, this is not something that I can give you,
it is something in the hands of Allah, and it's not a matter of authority and power.
This is not a power struggle,
Rasool ﷺ is telling him, this is a matter of religion, the earth belongs to Allah.
The man then responded and said, are we to present our throats to the Arabs in your defense.
And then if God gave you victory, see power go elsewhere then to us.
I mean, he understood that standing up with Muhammadﷺ is a risk
and we're going to have to fight for it.
He was telling Muhammadﷺ that
we're not going to sacrifice our lives and then see the power being transferred to someone else.
We won't have anything to do with you.
And he turned down the offer of Muhammadﷺ and rejected the message.
Bannu Aamir Bin Sa'saa(بنوعامر بن صعصعة), they went back to their homeland,
and there was an old man, among them who was a wise elder of theirs.
Because of his age, he wasn't able to attend the pilgrimage.
But whenever they would come back, he would ask them about the events that happened.
So, when they went back, they told him that
we met a young man, the grandson of Abdul-Mutallib(عبدالمطلب) from Quraish(قُرَيْشْ),
and he was claiming to be a prophet
and he came to us and we rejected him.
This old man said:
After putting his hand over his forehead, Could your mistake be put right?
Can its consequences be reversed?
I swear no descendant of Ismail(اِسْماعِيْل) ever made such a claim falsely.
It has to be true.
Where did your good judgment go?
This wise old man, told them
that none of the descendants of Ismailعليه السّلام has ever claimed to be a prophet.
This is not something common among the Arabs.
The Arabs don't know the concept of Prophet hood to claim it.
The Arabs were an illiterate nation.
They didn't have a history of Prophet hood.
The last prophet that they knew was, Ismailعليه السّلام which was more than 2000 years before that.
So, for them to claim Prophet hood is something that never happened.
So, this old man was saying it must be true.
Where was your good judgment?
And then he said;
Is this a mistake that can be rectified, is this something that we can fix?
There's another narration by Abu Naeem(ابو نعيم) and Al-Haakim(الحاكم) and Al-Bayhaqi(ألبيهقي).
I'm gonna have to read through this, It's quite long,
but I find it a fascinating conversation,
it shows the qualities of Abu Bakr As-Siddiqueرضي الله عنه.
Ali(علي) is the one who's narrating this story.
Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب), he says;
When God ordered his messenger to present himself to the tribes of the Arabs,
he left along with myself and Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) for Mina(مناء).
Mina(مناء) is where the camps are set.
Just like today in Hajj(حَجْ), that's where people spend the three days of Ayyam Tashreek(أيام تشريق).
That's where the tents are.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ is visiting these different Arab tribes
and Rasool Allah ﷺ used to always accompany Abu Bakr(ابو بكر) with him.
Because Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) was an expert in genealogy
Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) knew the history of the tribes, their names, their legends he knew a lot about them.
And this was an asset that Rasool Allah ﷺ was taking advantage of.
Because Abu Bakr As-Siddique(ابوبكرالصديق) was a walking encyclopedia, when it came to the genealogy of the Arab tribes.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ used to always accompany Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) with him, plus Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) was a well known man.
He has traveled widely, and he was known by the various Arab tribes.
Anyway, Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب), he says;
Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) god bless him, went forward and made his greetings.
He was in the very vanguard of good and an expert in genealogy.
So, he came to this Majlis(مجلس), to this meeting of this particular clan,
Abu Bakr As-Siddiqueرضي الله عنه walked up to them.
And when Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) says;
وَكَانَ سَبَّاقً عَلى كُلِّ خَيْرْ
He was at the vanguard of every good.
Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) was telling us that
in everything good, you would find Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) ahead of everyone else
Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) was first.
You know the story when Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) said;
Tonight, I'm going to do something that Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) didn't do.
And he went to Rasool Allah ﷺ and gave him half of his money.
And he said: O Rasool Allah, Did anybody else come to you?
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: Yes, Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) came to me and he gave all of his money.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) said, I'll never compete with him after this.
So, Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) is saying that Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) is ahead of every good.
Everything good, you'll find Abu Bakr(ابوبكر), the first.
He was the one who walked up to these men.
He greeted them, and then he said: From whom do you people come?
They said, We are from Rabiya(ربيعه),
the tribe of Rabiya(ربيعه), which were in the north east part of Arabia,
they might have been in the area of Iraq.
Rabiya(ربيعه), is a large tribe.
Abu Bakr(ابوبكر), now wants to narrow it down a little further.
They said, we're from Rabiya(ربيعه).
Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) said;
أمن هامها أم من لهازمها
It is translated here as from its mainstream, or from its branch,
actually a more accurate translation will be are you from the forehead?
Hamaha(هَامَهَا) means the forehead.
Are you from the forehead Or are you from the branches, the limbs,
meaning you are from the lower parts of the tribe.
They said, We are from the greatest mainstream of it, meaning we are the best.
Abu Bakr As-Siddiqueرضي الله عنه want to verify that claim
to realize whether they are the elites of their people, or they are from the layman.
So, Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) started his conversation, he said,
Is Auf(عوف) of you, of whom it said there is no Hurr(حر), no freeman in the Auf(عوف) valley
unfortunately, it's too many mistakes in the translation,
even though this is supposed to be a good translation of the book.
But there's still mistakes in there, correct it, heat thing is freeman, it's not heat, it's freeman.
Sometimes there are words in Arabic that are quite similar in meaning.
So, the translator might make a mistake in Qasra'a(قَصْرَه) or Fat'ha(فَتْهَا)
For example, in this word of heat
heat is Harr(حَرْ), and free is Hurr(حُرْ).
So, you just have a difference of a Dumma(ذَمَّهْ).
So, the translator thought that it is heat, but it is actually Hur(حُرْ).
Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) is saying is Auf(عوف) of you?
Of whom, it was said there is no free man in Auf(عوف)'s Valley.
This man, Auf(عوف) was from the tribe of Rabiya(ربيعه).
And he was such a strong man that everyone in the valley was so submissive to him.
They ended up saying that there's no one free in his Valley.
And by the way, in the culture of pre Islamic Arabia,
strength and power and sometimes even violence is viewed with respect.
This is one of the things that Islam came to change.
That oppression is not good.
So, Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) said: Is Auf(عوف) of you,
of whom it was said there is no free man in Auf(عوف)'s Valley.?
They said: No.
Does Bastaam Bin Qais Abu Luwaa(بسطام بن قيس صاحب اللواء) and Muntaha Al-Ahya(منتهى الأحياء) belong to you?
Is Al-Haofazan Bin Shuraik(الحوفزان بن شريق), the killer of kings and the robber of their souls, a kinsmen of yours?
No.
Is the Jassas Bin Murra(جساس بن مرة), the protector of honor and the defender of the neighbor from you?
They said: No.
Is Az-Muzdalaf(مزدلف), he of the unique turban from you?
Are you related to the kings of Kindaa(كندا)?
No.
Are you related to the kings of Laham(لخم)?
Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) said: So you're not from the mainstream, but you are from the Branch.
You can see the detailed information that Abu Bakr As-Siddiqueرضي الله عنه had about these people.
Now, a young man from Rabiya(ربيعه), stood up, his name is Daghfal(دغفل),
his beard just beginning to sprout, meaning he was young in age,
he jumped up and he grabbed the Bridle of Abu Bakr(ابوبكر)'s camel,
reciting those who asked of us will be asked of as for the burden of proof,
we neither know it, nor bare it as responsibility.
He then said; Hey you you ask, and we replied, hiding nothing from you.
We want to ask you something. Who are you.?
Now it's our turn, you ask us questions, we answered.
Give us a chance to ask you.
So, who are you?
He said, I'm a man from Quraish (قُرَيْشْ).
The youth commented well said, you are a people of leadership and nobility,
the vanguard and guide of the Arabs
there's nothing to complain about, you're from Quraish(قُرَيْشْ), you from the nobility.
Now let me narrate down.
What part of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) are you from?
Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) said: I am from Bannu Taim Bin Murra(بنو تيم بن مره).
Bannu Taim Bin Murra(بنو تيم بن مره) are small clan in Quraish(قُرَيْشْ),
wasn't famous, they weren't known for any special strength or uniqueness.
So, the young man said;
You have shown the target shooter where the bull's eye is.
He said: Is Qusa'e Bin Kalaab(قصئي بن كلاب), he, who killed at Makkah, those trying to conquer it.
A kinsmen of yours?
That man Qusae(قصئي) who drove the rest of them away
and brought his own people from all over and settle them in Makkah,
took over the temple and set Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) in the dwellings,
the man who was therefore known as the unifier,
and about whom a poet spoke the verse,
was it not your father who was called the unifier, by whom God brought together the tribes of Fihr(فهر)..
Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) said: No.
Were not Abd Manaf(عبد المناف) the ultimate giver of advice
and Abu Ghadarif(أبو الغدارف), the great leader of your stock.?
Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) said: No.
And Amr Bin Abd Manaf(عمرو بن عبد مناف), Hashim(هاشم),
who prepared bread and meat to the dish.
You remember when we talked about Hashim(هاشم).
So, he's now famous as being the one, who started a Sareed(سريد),
who prepared bread and meat into the dish, As-Sareed(ثريد) for his people and all of Makkah,
was he not of you?
the one of whom the poet said;
Amr Al-Ulaa(عمرو العلى) prepared the Sareed(ثريد) for his people
while the men of Makkah were destitute and under famine.
To him, they attribute both the journeys that of the winter and that of the summer,
Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) were as an egg,
which when split open, came to have its best part, it's yolk as, Ya Abd Manaf(يا عبد مناف),
they are the wealthy, as is no other known.
And they are those who say, Come on in to the guests,
They are those who strike down pure white sheep,
those who protect the innocent with their swords,
how fine for you, if you stay at their abode, they will protect you,
from all ills and accusations.
So, is he of you?
Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) said: No.
Then the youth continued, you must be related to Abd Al-Muttalib(عبدالمطلب)
that venerable man of much praise,
controller of the Makkah caravan
and the feeder of the birds of the skies and the wild beasts of the lions in the desert,
he, whose face shines forth like a moon on a dark night.
No, said, Abu Bakr(ابوبكر).
Now remember Abdul Muttalib(عبدالمطلب) they called him the feeder of the lions and the beast and the birds,
because of the hundred camels that he slaughtered and refused to take anything of it.
Then you must be of those who have the privilege of Ifadha(افادة).
No.
perhaps of those who have the privilege of Hijabah(حجابة).
No,
then those with the privilege of An-Nadwa(الندوة).
No.
then you must be of those who have the privilege of Sikaya(سقايه).
No,
are you then have those with the privilege of providing Rifadha(الرفادة).
No.
and he's answering no to all of these questions.
Now this was becoming too much for Abu Bakr(ابوبكر).
So, Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) just turned around
and tried to leave and he pulled the bridle out of the youth's hand.
The young man responded by saying,
he recited a line of poetry, he said,
صَادَفَ دَرْءُ السَّيْلِ دَرْءًا يدفعه فتارة يصدعه و تارة يهضبه
Your flood has met a greater flood that is coming from me.
Once it will crack it and another time, it will go over it.
So, you thought that you are flooded me?
I've shown you that I could send over you a greater flood.
And then he commented, well, I swear a brother of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ), if you had continued to hold out,
I would have proven to you that you belong to the lowest class of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) not to its elite.
Rasool Allah ﷺ came over smiling, after this interesting conversation,
and Ali(علي) told Abu Bakr(ابوبكر); well this Bedouin has turned out to be a disaster for you.
Abu Bakr As-Siddiqueرضي الله عنه, said: Yes.
And there is never a catastrophe without another that follows and calamity is compounded by words.
Ali(علي) then continued and said we went to a meeting that, we can see common dignity in the people,
and Abu Bakr(ابوبكر), he went to them and greeted them.
And he asked them where are you from?
They said we are from Bannu Shaibaan(بنو شيبان).
So, Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) came to report to Rasool Allah ﷺ and said these are people who have experience and power.
So, Abu Bakrرضي الله عنه he went to the group leaders
which were Mafrooq Bin Amr(مفروق بن عمرو) and Haani Bin Kubaisah(هاني بن قبيسه),
and Al-Muthanna Bin Harris(مثنى بن حارث), and An-Noman Bin Shuraik(نعمان بن شريق)
and the person who was closest to Abu Bakr As-Siddique(ابو بكر الصديق) was Mafrooq Bin Amr(مفروق بن عمرو),
and he was described as having two braids that came down to his chest.
So Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) asked him, How many are you in number?
Al-Mafrooq(المفروق) replied, We are more than 1000 strong.
And a few men can't beat 1000 as they say.
And then he said, and how would protection be with you?
He said, we go to the limit, and every people have their limit.
Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) then asked, and how is it when you make war with your enemies.
Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) is trying to assess their strength.
They said: When we meet in battle, we are the angriest of men,
we take great pride in our steeds than our sons,
care more for our swords than our camels.
Victory rests with Allah.
Sometimes He grants us victory, sometimes others victory over us.
You seems to be a member of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ).
So, Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) replied: Yes.
And then he said, have you heard of the Messenger of Allah?
So, Mafrooq(مفروق) said: We have heard that he says, he is, the Messenger of Allah.
Meaning we don't yet know but we've heard that rumor.
So, then Mafrooq(مفروق) wanted to hear from Muhammadﷺ,
after Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) has paved the way and open the conversation.
Now Rasool Allah ﷺ came in and he started speaking
and he spoke after Mafrooq(مفروق) asked him to, he said: What do you propound O brother of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ)?
He said, I call upon you to bear witness that there is no God but Allah alone, who has no associates
and that I'm the Messenger of Allah,
I asked you to shelter and protect me, until I can carry out,
what Allah has ordered me to do.
Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) came out against Allah's commands and have denied his messenger
they have sided with wrong against right, but Allah is All Powerful, All Praised.
So, Mafrooq(مفروق), he did like the words of Rasool Allah ﷺ, he asked him for some more.
Rasool Allah ﷺ recited him some is from Surat Al-An'aam(سورة الانعام).
Mafrooq(مفروق) said: And what else do you propound, O brother of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ),
I swear these are not words of any earthly mortal,
if they were we would know them to be.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ recited Ayaat(آيات) from Surat An-Nahal(سورة النحل).
Anyway, after Rasool Allah ﷺ has explained the message of Islam,
Mafrooq(مفروق), liked what he heard, but then he said that
we have people behind us and we cannot speak for them.
I mean, we were just a delegation from our people.
And he said that we cannot give a commitment now we have to go back and consult our people.
And he said words, he said;
I consider that abandoning our religion,
and following you in yours, because of one meeting we were having with you,
which had neither introduction nor follow up
and without our giving it full consideration,
nor examining what the consequences would be of what you suggest,
that would be a lapse in judgment, rashness, and inadequate consideration of consequences.
So, Mafrooq(مفروق), these people were very calm, they didn't want to rush into judgment.
They said, We have to think it over.
We can just leave our religion after one meeting with you.
So, you can see that there's a difference between these different tribes.
With Al-Ansaar(ألأنصار), they immediately accepted, because the grounds were prepared for them.
But with Bannu Shaibaa(بنو شيبه), they said;
I mean, there's there was no introduction to this, and there's no follow up, we can just convert right now.
So, let's go back to our people and consult them.
But I want you to also hear the opinion of Haani Bin Qubaisa(هاني بن قبيسه),
there were three leaders, one was religious one was political, and the other one was Tribal Affairs.
So, Mafrooq(مفروق) he spoke his opinion and now he wants to let Haani(هاني) speak.
So, Haani(هاني) said:
Actually, the words that I just read to you were the words of Haani(هاني).
And now they wanted to get the opinion of Harissa(حارثه),
so Al-Harissa(الحارثه) said: I heard and I liked what you said.
So, they were all impressed.
I was impressed by your words, but our answers should be that of Haani Bin Qubaisa(هاني بن قبيسه)
for us to leave our religion and follow you, after one sitting with us,
would be like us, taking residents between two pools of stagnant water
one Al-Yamama(يمامه) and other As-samawa(ألسماوة).
Rasool Ullah did not understand that.
He said, and what might those pools of stagnant water be?
Al-Muthanna(ألمثنى) replied, one of these is where the land extends to the Arab world
and the other is that of Persia and the rivers of Khusro(خسرو), Kisra(كسرى).
We will be reneging on a pact that Khusro(خسرو) has placed upon us,
to the effect that we would not cause an incident and not give sanctuary to a troublemaker.
This policy you suggest for us, is such a one thing that kings dislike.
As for those areas, bordering Arab lands, the blame of those so acting would be forgiven
and excuses for them, be accepted.
But for those areas next to Persia, those so acting would not be forgiven,
and no such excuses would be accepted.
If you want us to help you and protect you from whatever relates to Arab territories alone.
We would do so.
In case you didn't understand what Muthanna(مثنى) is referring to here.
The land of Bannu Shaibah(بنو شيبه) was bordering the Persian Empire.
So, their military leader who knows the contracts between them and the Persian Empire, Al-Muthanna(ألمثنى), he said,
we have an agreement between us and the Persians
that we will never give sanctuary to a troublemaker.
And this religion of yours is something that kings do not like.
So, look at the wisdom that he realized from his meeting with Rasool Allah ﷺ
that this is something that kings will not really like.
Because kings want to have authority in their hands to abuse others
and this is a religion that is to free people.
He said;
We cannot offer you protection from the Persian side but we can offer you protection from the Arab side.
So, the land that is bordering the Arabs, we will promise you that we will protect you from them,
but the area that is bordering Persia we cannot promise you anything,
we cannot stand in front of the Persian Empire, it's too much for us.
Rasool Allah ﷺ responded by saying;
Your reply is in no way bad for you have spoken eloquently and truthfully
you've been honest.
But God's religion can only be engaged in, by those who encompass it, from all sides.
Rasool Allah ﷺ did not want to have half a deal,
did not want to have a compromised deal,
Rasool Allah ﷺ wanted to have complete protection.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: The religion of Allah needs to be surrounded from every direction.
I want an absolute commitment to protect me,
you can say that I'm going to protect you from one side but not from the other.
What we can learn from this is that, in our negotiations and in our deals,
we need to keep in mind that the religion of Allah, needs to be held in high esteem.
And we should not bargain and negotiate in it.
And we should not compromise its terms.
And if the agreement does not fulfill the Islamic terms, we don't have to involve in it.
Rasool Allah ﷺ felt no need, in joining an agreement even though he knew his situation in Makkah.
He knew how difficult it was and he knew how badly he needs to leave.
Nevertheless, he did not want to enter into an agreement that was half hearted, halfway through.
And this is where you put your trust in Allahسبحانه وتعالى.
Rasool Allah ﷺ, left it up to Allahعَزّوجَلّ
and refused to accept that particular agreement from the people of Bannu Shaibah(بنو شيبه).
Ibn Is'haq(ابن اسحاق) , he goes on with the story of Al-Ansaar(ألأنصار).
Now who are Al-Ansaar(ألأنصار)?
Al-Aos Wal Khazraj(ألاوس ولخزرج) when they became Muslim were called Al-Ansaar(ألأنصار).
Which means, the protectors.
Al-Aos Wal Khazraj(ألاوس ولخزرج) were the two Arab tribes that were living in Madina
and they are descendants of the branch of Kahtaan(قحطان)
see the Arabs divided into Adnan(عدنان) and Kahtaan(قحطان).
Kahtaan(قحطان) are the Arabs of Yemen
and Adnan(عدنان) are the descendants of Ismailعليه السّلام.
So, Al-Aos Wal Khazraj(ألاوس ولخزرج) were from Kahtaan(قحطان)
They were neighboring three Jewish tribes,
Bannu Quraidha(بنو قريضه),
Bannu Qainuqah(بنو قينقاع)
and Bannu Nadhir(بنو نضير).
Al-Madina was unique in that, it offered a protection from three sides.
There were two rocky tracks on the east and west,
which are inaccessible for armies to cross
and then there were the trees, the farms of Madina towards the south.
So, the only direction where an army can attack Madina is from the north,
so it has this natural protection from three sides.
Rasool Allah ﷺ visited the camp of Al-Aos Wal Khazraj(ألاوس ولخزرج), in Hajj(حَجْ)
actually, at the time he visited Al-Khazraj(الخزرج).
Rasool Allah ﷺ when he came in, he asked them, who are you?
They said: We are from Al-Khazraj(الخزرج).
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: Are you the allies of the Jews?
They said: Yes.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: Can I speak to you?
They agreed.
So, they sat down and Rasool Allah ﷺ invited them to Islam.
Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله),
they were very eager to hear what Rasool Allah ﷺ said.
And they immediately accepted, and they told Rasool Allahﷺ;
We have left our own people, for they have such discord and dissension between them, not found in any other.
Perhaps God may unite them through you, we will go forth among them and invite them to you,
presenting to them this religion we have accepted from you.
If God should unite them around you, then no one will be dearer to us, then you.
This immediate acceptance of Islam, by the small group of Al-Khazraj(الخزرج), the number was six.
How come it happened that way?
How come Ansaar(أنصار) were not resistant to the message of Islam, like the other Arab tribes?
There are few reasons.
Number one,
the people of Madina were in a constant warfare among themselves.
Al-Aos Wal Khazraj(ألاوس ولخزرج) were fighting an age old war between themselves,
imagine two tribes living in the same city, and they are fighting with each other,
so they were earning for peace.
And when these men of Al-Khazraj(الخزرج) heard the message of Rasool Allah ﷺ, they said;
Maybe Allah will unite us through you, we really need peace,
we've been at each other's throats for so long.
That's one reason.
Second reason,
The Aos(أوس) and Khazraj(خزرج) had a natural, monotheism was appealing to them,
because they were neighbors of the Jews.
And the Arabs used to see the religion of the Jews being superior to theirs.
Why is that?
The Jews were learned.
They had scripture,
they had teachings,
they had knowledge,
while the religion of the Arabs was merely myths, and idols
and killing of their daughters.
So, if it wasn't for the Jewish prejudice and arrogance, towards the Arabs,
most likely Al-Aos Wal Khazraj(ألاوس ولخزرج) would have been Jewish.
But the reason why they didn't convert,
is because the Jews used to always treat them as if they are a lower class
and as if the Jewish religion is only suitable for the elites.
And sometimes there will be conflicts between the Arabs and the Jews.
So, the Jews would say, that this is a time of a prophet that will appear
and when he comes out, we will follow him,
and we will kill you, like the people of Aad(عاد) were killed.
So, number three, the Arabs also knew that this is a time of a prophet.
So, the Arabs of Al-Aos Wal Khazraj(ألاوس ولخزرج) were prepared for this message.
Allahسبحانه وتعالى has prepared them.
They knew about the monotheistic religion of the Jews,
and they knew the value of to Tauheed(توحيد), the oneness of Allah,
they knew that the Prophet is coming, and they needed peace.
And number four,
a few years before the Hijrah(هجرة) of Rasool Allah ﷺ,
a battle called Buaath(بعاث) occurred between Al-Aos Wal Khazraj(ألاوس ولخزرج)
this was such a violent war, it ended up killing most of the current leadership of both tribes.
So, imagine having two clans with the majority of their leaders, their seniors killed.
So, now you have a people that are looking for leadership,
they do not have an established structure of leadership among them.
So, when they heard the message of Rasool Allah ﷺ,
they were looking forward to have him, lead them.
So, all of these were elements when combined together,
it made Madina a very fertile ground for the spread of Islam.
And some of these things were mentioned, for example, there's a statement by Ayesha رضي الله عنها,
she said that the war of Buaath(بعاث) was preparation by Allahسبحانه وتعالى for the migration of Rasool Allah ﷺ
and she says:
قُتِلَتْ ثَرَوَاتُهُمْ
Their leaders were killed.
Because remember, we said that the people who tend to me the most resistant to the truth, are who.?
The leaders of a society.
now Al-Aos Wal Khazraj(ألاوس ولخزرج) do not have that hurdle in front of them.
The leaders were killed in the Battle of Buaath(بعاث)
And Ibn Is'haqq(اِبْنِ اِسْحَاقْ), he says,
One way, which God facilitated their acceptance of Islam
was that the Jews were there, with them in their country,
these were followers of the Scripture and men of knowledge,
though they themselves were polytheists and idol worshippers,
they had previously attacked these Jews in their territories.
And whenever a dispute had arisen
the latter had told them a prophet will now be sent, his day is coming
we will follow him and give you the same fate as that of the peoples of Aad(عاد) and Iram(إرم).
So, Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله)
you can see how Allah was preparing Al-Aos Wal Khazraj(ألاوس ولخزرج) for this great responsibility.
Now,
وَعَسَى أَنْ تَكْرَهُوا شَيْئًا وَهُوَ خَيْرٌ لَكُمْ
You might dislike something but in it, is a lot of good for you.
This war that happened between Al-Aos Wal Khazraj(ألاوس ولخزرج) and killed many of them,
even though it caused a lot of bloodshed and harm to them.
It was one of the reasons that brought them closer to Islam.
Anyway, so these six men accepted Islam
and they told Rasool Allahﷺ, we'll go back to our people and start preaching the message.
And they made an appointment with Rasool Allah ﷺ to meet him next year in the season of Hajj(حَجْ).
So, a year passed by and now the season of Hajj(حَجْ) approached, the six came back as 12.
We had the Original Six, in addition to them six more.
The earlier, six were all from Al-Khazraj(الخزرج)
there's one narration that says five were from Al-Khazraj(الخزرج), and one from Al-Aos(الاوس).
Now, in the second year, they were 12,
10 of them were from Al-Khazraj(الخزرج) and 2 from Al-Aos(الاوس)
They came to Rasool Allah ﷺ and they gave him Pledge of Allegiance.
And it was called the pledge of the women.
Even though none of them, was a female.
These 12 were males, but the Pledge of Allegiance was called Baiyah-Tun-Nisaa(بيعة النساء),
the Pledge of Allegiance of the women.
Why?
Because it did not include within its terms, any pledge of fighting.
The terms of the pledge were.!
We pledge to the Messenger of Allah, on the night of the first meeting, at Aqabah(عقبه)
that we would not associate any other God with Allah,
that we would not steal,
commit fornication,
kill our children,
make false accusations,
nor disobey him in anything good.
He told us, if you keep to this, you shall have paradise.
But if you give up any of this
and you are punished for it in this world, then that will provide the atonement for you.
But if it is overlooked until Judgment Day,
it will be up to Allah to decide whether to punish or to forgive you.
So, you can notice here that the pledge includes them, committing themselves to Islam
and worshiping as individuals,
but it does not include any terms relating to protection or fighting.
And that's why it was called Baiyah-Tun-Nisaa(بيعة النساء).
Why was it given this name?
because this was the pledge of allegiance, that women would give to Muhammadﷺ.
Now there's a Fiqh(فقه) issue to be dealt with here,
you notice here that these are major sins,
stealing,
fornicating,
killing children,
making false accusations,
these are all major sins.
And there is a hadd(حد) a punishment prescribed.
Now, Rasool Allah ﷺ says here, that if the punishment is fulfilled in this world, that will forgive you of the sin.
However, if the punishment is not done in this world,
than it is up to Allah, to either forgive or punish.
So, if somebody steals
and they are punished for their stealing by the cutting of the hand, then that forgives the sin, that forgives the sin.
The sin is gone.
But if the punishment is not implemented,
on the Day of Judgment, it is up to Allah to forgive or to punish for that particular sin.
And that relates to Al-Kabaer(ألكبائر), the major sins.
Now Rasool Allah ﷺ appointed Mus'ab Bin Umair(مصعب بن عمير) to go and teach the people of Madina Islam.
You can call him an ambassador,
you can call him a teacher,
you can call him a scholar,
he had all of these roles in one.
Mus'ab Ibn Umairرضي الله عنه came from a wealthy family in Quraish(قُرَيْشْ),
Mus'ab Ibn Umair(مصعب ابن عمير) was the most spoiled young man in Makkah, before Islam.
He he used to wear the most expensive clothes, he would have the best perfume
and his mother was taking care of him.
So, she was very wealthy woman and she didn't have many kids.
So, she was taking very good care of them.
And he was very spoiled.
He became Muslim, his mother boycotted him, she stood against him.
And Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله) Mus'ab Ibn Umair(مصعب ابن عمير), who was wealthy turns from wealth to poverty
from living a spoiled life, to living a tough and harsh life.
And when Mus'ab Ibn Umairرضي الله عنه was killed in the Battle of Uhud(أحد)
the witnesses of his burial said: He did not even leave behind enough money to buy a coffin.
And obviously since he's a Shaheed(شهيد), he's not wrapped in any special clothes.
But when he was fighting, he had on himself one piece of cloth that was not sufficient to cover him.
So, they said whenever we would cover his face, his feet would appear.
And whenever we would cover his feet, his face would appear.
So, they went to Rasool Allah ﷺ and said: What can we do?
He said, Well cover his face, and then use some tree leaves to cover his feet.
Mus'ab Ibn Umair(مصعب ابن عمير) was given this difficult task
and major responsibility of being, the personal representative of Rasool Allah ﷺ in Madina.
So, now Mus'ab Ibn Umair(مصعب ابن عمير) left Makkah, and he went to reside in Madina.
Since Al-Aos Wal Khazraj(ألاوس ولخزرج) were enemies.
Mus'ab Ibn Umair(مصعب ابن عمير) had to lead them in Salah(صلاة),
because none of them would accept praying behind an Imam from the other tribe.
One day, Mus'ab Ibn Umairرضي الله عنه, was with As'ad Ibn Zurara(أسعد إبن زراره), who was his host,
As'ad Ibn Zurara(أسعد إبن زراره), was the one, who was hosting Mus'ab Ibn Umair(مصعب إبن عمير).
So, they went to visit some of the Muslims, they went into this farm garden,
and they were sitting there, and the Muslims were coming to them to learn.
They would come and meet with Mus'ab Ibn Umair(مصعب ابن عمير) and he would teach them,
he would hold Halaqaat(حلقات), sessions for them, in this place.
They happen to go to a neighborhood of Madina that was part of Al-Aos(الاوس)'s territory.
And remember that, the majority of the Muslims were from which tribe Al-Aos(الاوس) or Al-Khazraj(الخزرج).?
From Al-Khazraj(الخزرج).!
So, Islam now was spreading with speed among Al-Khazraj(الخزرج),
but it wasn't catching up with Al-Aos(الاوس).
So, now Mus'ab Ibn Umair(مصعب ابن عمير) is trying to make inroads within Al-Aos(الاوس).
So, they went to an area that is in the land of Al-Aos(الاوس), and they sat there.
The leaders of Al-Aos(الاوس) were close by.
Sa'ad Ibn Muadh(سعد بن معاذ) and Usaid Bin Khudhair(أسيد بن خضير).
Sa'ad Ibn Muadh(سعد بن معاذ) spotted Mus'ab Ibn Umair(مصعب ابن عمير) and As'ad Ibn Zurara(أسعد إبن زراره).
Sa'ad Ibn Muadh(سعد بن معاذ) told Usaid Bin Khuzair(أسيد بن خضير), I want you to go to those two men
and tell them that, we don't want them around misguiding the weak and foolish among us.
And if it wasn't for the fact that As'ad Ibn Zurara(أسعد إبن زراره) was my relative, I would have done that myself
As'ad Ibn Zurara(أسعد إبن زراره), was in a position
that Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله), Allah prepared him to carry this role of hosting Mus'ab(مصعب).
As'ad Ibn Zurara(أسعد إبن زراره) was from Al-Khazraj(الخزرج).
But he was a cousin of the head of Al-Aos(الاوس).
So, on the mother's side, he was a relative of Sa'ad Ibn Muadh(سعد بن معاذ).
So, he had ties to both tribes both to Al-Aos(الاوس) and Al-Khazraj(الخزرج).
Sa'ad Ibn Muadh(سعد بن معاذ) told Usaid Bin Khuzair(أسيد بن خضير), I want you to go and kick them out.
And if it wasn't for the fact that As'ad Ibn Zurara(أسعد إبن زراره) is my relative, I would have done that myself.
So now, Usaid Bin Khuzair(أسيد بن خضير), went up carrying his spear towards Mus'ab Ibn Umair(مصعب ابن عمير) and As'ad Ibn Zurara(أسعد إبن زراره).
As'ad Ibn Zurara(أسعد إبن زراره), saw him coming,
and he told Mus'ab Ibn Umair(مصعب ابن عمير); This is a leader of his people, be sincere with him.
Do your best, because if he becomes Muslim, many people will follow him.
Mus'ab Ibn Umair(مصعب ابن عمير) said: If he listens, I would!
So, now Usaid Bin Khuzair(أسيد بن خضير) came
and he stood above them carrying his spear, speaking to them in a very harsh tone.
He said;
we don't want you around here, misleading the weak and ignorant among us.
And then he said, and if you care about your lives, you better get out of here.
Otherwise, this is my spear, you could be killed.
So, he threatened them.
And one of the attendees of the Halaqah(حلقه).
He said: Well, you are the one who was misleading us, and he started an argument.
Mus'ab Ibn Umair(مصعب ابن عمير) responded calmly by saying,
how about you sit down, and you hear, what I say.
If you like it, you can accept it, if you don't, you can reject it.
Usaid Bin Khuzair(أسيد بن خضير) said: Fair enough.
And he sat down, he stuck his spear in the ground and he sat down.
Mus'ab Ibn Umair(مصعب ابن عمير) started reciting to him Ayaat(آيات) of Qur'an, giving them Da'wah(دعوة) explaining Islam.
As'ad Ibn Zurara(أسعد إبن زراره) said;
even without him speaking a word,
We were able to see Islam entering his heart, because of the calmness in his face
and the radiance of light coming out of it.
We could see it on his face.
And when Mus'ab Ibn Umair(مصعب ابن عمير) finished with his session with Usaid Bin Khuzair(أسيد بن خضير),
Usaid Bin Khuzair(أسيد بن خضير) said: What does one have to do to join your religion.
Mus'ab Ibn Umair(مصعب ابن عمير) told him wash yourself and you come and pray.
Usaid Bin Khuzair(أسيد بن خضير), he did that and then he came back,
and he said; Now I'm going to send you a man, if he becomes Muslim all of his people will follow him.
Usaid Bin Khuzair(أسيد بن خضير) went to Sa'ad Bin Muadh(سعد بن معاذ).
Now Sa'ad Bin Muadh(سعد بن معاذ), saw Usaid Bin Khuzair(أسيد بن خضير) and he said;
I swear by Allah that he's coming to us with a different face than, the one he left us with.
The Arabs had this Farasah(فراسه) thing,
Farasah(فراسه) is the art of reading the face.
And it is reported that Ash-Shafa'i(الشافعي) went to Yemen to learn this art.
So, it was an art that existed.
And a Chinese brother, a Muslim brother said that also in China, some people have this art.
You look at the face of a person and you try to read what is in their hearts,
what is what they're thinking about what's going on with them.
There's an incident when Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) was a Khalifah(خليفه),
he saw a man passing by, and he said;
This man is either a soothsayer or he has been a soothsayer in the past.
So, they went and asked this man he said:
Yes, I used to be a Kahin (كاهن).
I used to be a fortune teller or a soothsayer?
He said; Yes, I was a soothsayer,
So Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) just knew it by looking at his face.
So, Sa'ad Ibn Muadh(سعد بن معاذ), when he looked at the face of Usaid Bin Khuzair(أسيد بن خضير),
he said; He's coming back to us with a different face
than the face he left us with.
Sa'ad Ibn Muadh(سعد بن معاذ) told him what happened.
Usaid Bin Khuzair(أسيد بن خضير) said; Everything is fine. Don't worry about it.
There's a slight problem, however,
and that is that Bannu Harris(بنو الحارث) want to kill As'ad Ibn Zurara(أسعد إبن زراره)
because they know that he's your cousin.
In case you don't remember the names, As'ad Ibn Zurara(أسعد إبن ضراره) is the man with Mus'ab Ibn Umair(مصعب ابن عمير)
and he's the cousin of Sa'ad Ibn Muadh(سعد بن معاذ).
Usaid Bin Khuzair(أسيد بن خضير) said;
Bannu Hariss(بنو الحارث) this is a branch of Al-Khazraj(الخجرج), want to kill As'ad Ibn Zurara(أسعد إبن زراره),
because he is your relative.
Usaid Bin Khuzair(أسيد بن خضير), made up the whole story, that wasn't true.
The whole reason why, he made it up, is he wants Sa'ad Ibn Muadh(سعد بن معاذ) to go and meet Mus'ab Ibn Umair(مصعب ابن عمير).
Sa'ad Ibn Muadh(سعد بن معاذ) stood up angry and he said they want to kill my cousin.
He picked up the spear and he left and he said, you haven't done me any good.
And he went there and he came, and you can see anger on his face.
And he was carrying a spear, Mus'ab Ibn Umair(مصعب ابن عمير) saw him coming.
As'ad Ibn Zurara(أسعد إبن زراره), told Mus'ab(مصعب), this is the leader of his people.
Do the best you can.
اُصْدُقَ الله فِيْكْ
Sa'ad Ibn Muadh(سعد بن معاذ) came
and Sa'ad Ibn Muadh(سعد بن معاذ), he just took a look at the meeting.
And he realized that the story that Usaid Bin Khuzair(أسيد بن خضير) reported was fabricated
because it didn't seem that they were terrified,
it didn't seem that there was a plot to kill As'ad Bin Zurarah(أسعد بن زراره).
Otherwise, they would have been acting differently.
So, Sa'ad Ibn Muadh(سعد بن معاذ) realized that Usaid Bin Khuzair(أسيد بن خضير) has made up the story
because he wants him to come and see what's happening.
Sa'ad Ibn Muadh(سعد بن معاذ), came and he told As'ad Ibn Zurara(أسعد إبن زراره), he said;
Why are you doing this to me.
Why are you bringing this man to my territory?
You're taking advantage of your relationship with me,
you want to mislead the ignorant and the weak among us.
Mus'ab Ibn Umair(مصعب ابن عمير) responded and said;
How about you sit down and hear what I have to say?
If you like it, you can accept it, if you don't, you can reject it.
Sa'ad Ibn Muadh(سعد بن معاذ) agreed and he sat down.
Notice here the people of Madina are open minded.
They don't have the sense of hostility that existed in Makkah.
They were willing to listen, so Sa'ad Ibn Muadh(سعد بن معاذ) sat down,
Mus'ab Ibn Umair(مصعب ابن عمير), the choice of Rasool Allah ﷺ for this mission,
Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله) he had the Hikmah(حكمة) and the wisdom of a Daiyah(داعيه), somebody who preach Islam.
He started giving Sa'ad Ibn Muadh(سعد بن معاذ) a message
As'ad Ibn Zurara(أسعد إبن زراره) said, I can read in his face, the fact that he wants to become a Muslim.
And when the conversation finished Sa'ad Ibn Muadh(سعد بن معاذ) accepted Islam.
And what was the first action Sa'ad Ibn Muadh(سعد بن معاذ) did.?
He went to his people and he said, What is your opinion of me.?
They said, You are the wisest among us, and you are our leader.
Sa'ad Ibn Muadh(سعد بن معاذ) said: Well, none of you speak to me, and I will speak to none of you,
until you become Muslim.
The narrator of the Hadith(حديث) said;
By the end of that evening, every house among Bannu-Al-Ash'hal(بنو الإشحل) was Muslim.
The whole clan of Bannu-Al-Ash'hal(بنو الإشحل), which were a branch of Al-Aos(ألاوس).
So, now a huge breakthrough was made within Al-Aos(ألاوس).
So, you have both Al-Aos wal Khazraj(ألاوس ولخزرج).
صَلَّى الله عَلى سَيَّدِنَا محمد وَعَلى اَلِهِ وَ صَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ